Inventory of the George Weigel papers
Hoover Institution Archives
George Weigel papers
1978-1992
2010C7
Weigel, George, 1951-
13 manuscript boxes (5.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, memoranda, minutes, and printed matter relating to Weigel's role as a theologian and scholar, the role of religion, specifically from the Christian and Catholic point of view, in American foreign policy, peace and disarmament movements, and activities of the World without War Council and the Ethics and Public Policy Center..
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1951, April 17 Born, Baltimore Maryland
1973 B.A. (magna cum laude), St. Mary's Seminary and University, Baltimore, MD
1974-1975 Lecturer in theology, Christian Brothers College, Orangeville, Ontario
1975 M.A. (summa cum laude), University of St. Michael's College, Toronto, Ontario
1975-1977 Assistant professor of theology and assistant dean of studies, St. Thomas Seminary, Washington, DC
1975-1978 Instructor in religion and pastoral theology, Religious Education Center, Seattle, WA
1977-1984 Scholar in residence, World without War Council of Greater Seattle, Seattle
1980-1984 Founder and director of Cathedral Fellowships in World Affairs
1980-2005 Member of executive committee, Institute on Religion and Democracy
1981-1984 Member of Board of Regents, Seattle University Co-director of American Initiatives Project, World without War Council
1982-1984 Member of advisory committee on ethical values, U.S. Information Agency
1983-1995 Member of board of directors, Rural Development Institute
1984 Mars Lecturer on theology, ethics, war, and peace, Northwestern University
1984-1985 Research fellow at Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars
1985-1989 President, James Madison Foundation, Washington, DC
1986-1989 Associate, Center on Religion and Society
1987-1992 Member, Keston-USA; Member, Puebla Institute
1987-Present Member, Ad Hoc Committee on Religious Liberty; Editor and principal author, American Purpose; Co-director, U.S. Institute of Peace Seminar
1989-1996 President, Ethics and Public Policy Center, Washington, DC
1996-2007 Senior fellow, Ethics and Public Policy Center
1996-Present Director of the Catholic Studies program, Ethics and Public Policy Center
2005 Author, The Cube and the Cathedral: Europe, America, and Politics without God, Basic Books (New York, NY)
2008-Present Distinguished senior fellow, Ethics and Public Policy Center
Sources and Other Resources:
"George Weigel." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2009. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 24 Sept. 2010
George Weigel. n.d. Web. http://georgeweigel.blogspot.com/ 24 Sept. 2010
"The Syndicated Column of George Weigel: The Catholic Difference." Denver Catholic Register: The Archdiocese of Denver, 2010. http://www.archden.org/index.cfm/ID/342. Web. 24 Sept. 2010
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, memoranda, minutes, and printed matter relating to Weigel's role as a theologian and scholar, the role of religion, specifically from the Christian and Catholic point of view, in American foreign policy, peace and disarmament movements, and activities of the World without War Council and the Ethics and Public Policy Center.
The bulk of material relates specifically to Weigel's work as a member of the World without War Council, the James Madison Foundation, and the Ethics and Public Policy Center. Extensive documentation is also present regarding Weigel's role in the Millennium Appeal for freedom of religion in the Soviet Union that was sent to Mikhail Gorbachev.
Materials of interest include booklets regarding the role religious leaders can play in world peace and disarmament.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Religion and international affairs.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Religion.; Peace.; Pacifism.; Disarmament.; Catholic Church.; World without War Council.; Ethics and Public Policy Center (Washington, D.C.)
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1979-1988 (Box 1)
  Consists of correspondence between Weigel and private individuals as well as correspondence with members of related organizations. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Archdiocese of Baltimore, 1980-1982 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Archdiocese of Seattle, 1980-1982 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Kontos, C. William, 1985 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Lutheran Church in America/Pacific Northwest Synod, 1979 May (Folder 1: 4)
  - Martin, Diarmuid, 1988 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Schiffer, Richard, 1987 (Folder 1: 6)
    Ambassador, Assistant Secretary of State, Bureau of Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs, United States Department of State
  - Zagano, Phyllis, 1983 September 27 (Folder 1: 7)
- Organization and project records, 1976-1992 (Box 1-10)
  Contains documents related to organizations and specific projects Weigel was involved in. The bulk of the materials come from Weigel's involvement with the World Without War Council, the Ethics and Public Policy Center, and the Millennium Appeal to Mikhail Gorbachev (1988) for freedom of religion in the Soviet Union. Arranged alphabetically by name of project or organization.
  - Ethics and Public Policy Center (EPPC), 1988-1989 (Folder 1: 8-11)
  - EPPC Conference, September 16-18, 1988 (Folder 1: 12)
  - EPPC Sollicitudo Rei Socialis Conference, March 18, 1988 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Foreign Service Institute (FSI) Senior Seminars, 1985-1991 (Folder 1-2)
    Includes seminar materials, notes, and related correspondence. Arranged by seminar date
    - 1987 October 5-7 (Folder 1: 14)
    - 1988 March 2 (Folder 1: 15)
    - 1988 April 18-22 (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1988 June 2-3 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1988 September (Folder 2: 3)
    - 1988 September 14-16 (Folder 2: 4)
    - 1989 March 7-8 (Folder 2: 5)
    - 1989 May 18 (Folder 2: 6)
    - 1989 September 25-26 (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1990 May 23-24 (Folder 2: 8)
    - 1991 January 15 (Folder 2: 9)
  - James Madison Foundation file, 1986-1987 (Folder 2-3)
    - Congressional work, 1986 (Folder 2: 10-11)
      Includes correspondence, newsletters, collected materials and clippings, and other materials related to the foundation and their work with Congressman John Miller
    - Congressional work, (contd.), 1986 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Weigel's resignation from Congressman Miller's staff and related materials, 1987 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Closure information, 1987 August (Folder 3: 3)
  - Millennium Appeal project, 1988-1989 (Folder 3-6)
    Consists of materials pertaining to an appeal to Mikhail Gorbachev for freedom of religion in the Soviet Union. Includes correspondence, notes, and related documents
    - Book project, 1988-1989 (Folder 3: 4)
      Includes documents in Russian and Ukrainian
    - Chronology, 1988 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Folder 3: 6-8)
    - Database, 1987-1988 (Folder 3: 9-10)
    - Distribution, first and second edition, 1988-1989 (Folder 4: 1-2)
    - Distribution, third edition, 1989 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Press conference, 1988 April (Folder 4: 4)
    - Press coverage, 1988 (Folder 4)
      - America, 1988 May 14 (Folder 4: 5)
      - Christianity Today, 1988 June 17 (Folder 4: 6)
      - Congressional Record, 1988 May 17 (Folder 4: 7)
      - Keston News Service, 1988 May 12 (Folder 4: 8)
      - National Catholic Register, 1988 May 15 (Folder 4: 9)
      - New York Times, 1988 April 26 (Folder 4: 10)
      - Washington Post, 1988 April 29 (Folder 4: 11)
      - Washington Times, 1988 April 26, April 29 (Folder 4: 12)
      - Miscellany, 1988 April-September (Folder 4: 13)
      - Press coverage set, 1988 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Project records, 1987-1988 (Folder 5: 1-3)
    - Project report, 1988 June (Folder 5: 4)
    - World Without War Council (WWWC) regional projects, 1988 (Folder 5: 5)
    - Signatories, circa 1988, undated (Folder 5: 6-9)
      Consists of completed forms and related correspondence for those whose signatures appeared on the appeal
    - "Assessing Religious Freedom in the Soviet Union: One Year After the Millennium" conference, 1989 (Folder 6: 1-2)
      Includes follow-up information to the Millennium Appeal and other related documents
  - National Association of Evangelicals (NAE) and Peace, Freedom, and Security Studies (PFSS) materials, 1984-1992 (Folder 6-7)
    - Advisory committee, 1984-1987 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Correspondence course, 1989 May 24 (Folder 6: 4)
      Includes course materials and related documents
    - General information, 1984-1992 (Folder 6: 5-8)
    - Guidelines on Peace Freedom and Security Studies booklet, critiques, responses, and other information, circa 1985-1986 (Folder 6: 9-10)
    - Northwest Regional PFSS Program, 1987 November 23 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Programs, 1988-1989 (Folder 7: 2)
    - NAE/Union Seminary consultation, 1987 December 10 (Folder 7: 3)
    - WWWC involvement and Bob Pickus correspondence, 1984-1986 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Washington World Affairs Fellows (WWAF) records and financial information, circa 1986-1987 (Folder 7: 5-6)
  - World Without War Council (WWWC) records, 1986-1992 (Folder 7-9)
    - General documents, 1986-1992 (Folder 7: 7-10)
    - Board of directors meetings and related documents, 1987-1988 (Folder 7: 11)
    - Chicago office, 1988-1989 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Introductory materials, circa 1980-1984 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Midwest office, 1985-1986 (Folder 8: 2)
    - Northern California office, 1985-1989 (Folder 8: 3-7)
    - Seattle office, 1985-1986 (Folder 8: 8-9)
    - Seattle office, 1985-1991 (Folder 9: 1-6)
    - Study Guide to Bishops Statement The Challenge of Peace: God's Promise and Our Response, 1983 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Other organizations, projects, and collected items, 1983-1988 (Folder 9-10)
    - Ad-Hoc Committee on Religious Liberty, 1987-1988 (Folder 9: 8-9)
    - Evangelicals, 1983-1985 (Folder 10: 1)
    - "Reestablishing and Extending the Idea of the Common Good" project, 1993 (Folder 10: 2)
      A joint project between the James Madison Foundation and the WWWC
    - Simon, William E. speech at University of Notre Dame, 1985 October 15 and 1976-1985 (Folder 10: 3)
      Includes text of speech, related correspondence, and other writings by Simon
    - Target Seattle, 1982 (Folder 10: 4)
    - Wilson Quarterly project, 1986 (Folder 10: 5)
- Speeches, writings and conference materials, 1978-1989 (Box 10-13)
  Includes materials related to conferences, workshops, seminars and other speaking engagements in which Weigel participated, as well as some of his writings and related materials. Arranged by organization or title.
  - American Bar Association (ABA) National Security Workshop, Deception and Deterrence in "Wars of National Liberation," State-Sponsored Terrorism, and Other Forms of Secret Warfare, 1987 May 20-21 (Folder 10: 6)
  - ABA workshop, The Vietnam Debate: A Fresh Look at the Arguments, 1986 October 17-18 (Folder 10: 7)
    Includes Weigel's article "'Vietnam' and the transformation of the American Catholic Debate on War and Peace"
  - "An Appeal for the Religious Freedom in the Soviet Union on the Occasion of the Millennium of Christianity in the Kievan Rus,", 1988 (Folder 10: 8)
    Includes drafts and related correspondence
  - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency/Strategic Defense Initiative correspondence, 1986-1987 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities Campus Ministers, 1981 February 28 and 1981 January-March (Folder 10: 10)
  - Cardinal Mindszenty Foundation Conference, 1986 April 19 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Carnegie Council on Ethics and International Affairs Seminar, 1986 December 12 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Christian Century Colloquium, 1983 February 18 and 1981-1983 (Folder 10: 13)
    Includes correspondence, clippings and information regarding Bishop Armstrong
  - Christian College Coalition American Studies Program Seminar, 1985 December 4 (Folder 10: 14)
  - "Christian-Marxist Dialogue on Human Rights,", 1989 September 29-October 7 and 1989 January-November (Folder 10: 15)
  - "Christian Responsibility in an Election Year" at St. Marks Church, 1980 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Communion and liberation lecture, Catholic University, 1988 May (Folder 11: 2)
  - CRS/James Madison Foundation "After the Threat" conference, 1989 January-April (Folder 11: 3)
  - CSIS/Washington Quarterly colloquium, 1988 June (Folder 11: 4)
  - Denominational executives retreat, 1981 June 2 (Folder 11: 5)
  - English Speaking Union Lecture, 1981 May 2 and 1981 April-May (Folder 11: 6)
  - "Exorcising Wilson's Ghost: Morality and Foreign Policy in America's Third Century," Washington Quarterly, 1987 (Folder 11: 7)
    Includes draft and copy of published version
  - Foreign Policy Association, "1985 National Great Decisions Leadership Conference,", 1985 September 8-10 (Folder 11: 8)
  - George Mason University, Nuclear War Education Conference, 1986 April 10-12 (Folder 11: 9)
  - "Great Thinkers and the Arms Race,", 1979-1980, undated (Folder 11: 10)
  - "International Human Rights Quotient,", undated (Folder 11: 11)
  - Lithuanian Catholic groups, 1987 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Lithuanian Catholic Religious Group and the 100th U.S. Congress, 1987 (Folder 11: 13)
  - National Federation of Priests Council Disarmament Resolution, 1978 (Folder 11: 14)
  - 1979 Northwest Religious Education Congress, Yakima, WA, 1979 January-October (Folder 11: 15)
  - 1980 Northwest Religious Education Congress, Seattle (Folder 11: 16)
  - Seafirst Retreat, 1982 March 3-5 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations (SHAFR) Conference on Peace Research in History (CPRH) Seminar, 1986 June 26 and 1986 February-May (Folder 12: 2)
  - UN Special Rapporteur on Religious Intolerance: UNHRC; meeting with Schifter, 1986 September 10 (Folder 12: 3)
  - US State Department Relations with Non-Government Organizations (NGOs) discussion, 1985 October 11 (Folder 12: 4)
  - US State Department Commission for Security and Cooperation in Europe briefing, 1988 April 7 and 1987-1988 (Folder 12: 5)
  - USIA Worldnet, 1988 April (Folder 12: 6)
  - US Institute of Peace (USIP) Public Workshop on Pacifism and Citizenship, 1988 September 28 (Folder 12: 7)
  - USIP Democracy and Peace Workshop, 1989 April 17 and 1989 April-May (Folder 12: 8)
  - University of Washington course "Arms, Citizens and the Shape of the Future,", 1981-1983 (Folder 12: 9)
  - University of Washington Spectrum course, "Understanding the Arms Race", 1982 (Folder 12: 10)
  - University of Washington Strategic Seminar, 1981-1983 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Peace Bishops and the Arms Race (PB/AR) booklet and related materials, 1982-1983 (Folder 12: 12-14)
  - PB/AR booklet, 1982-1984 (Folder 13: 1)
  - PB/AR reprints from Catholic newspapers and publications, 1981 (Folder 13: 2-5)
- Memorabilia and Photographs, 1979-1984 (Box 13)
  Name tags from various speaking events and engagements as well as photographs of Weigel alone or with colleagues.
  - Name tags from various events, 1979-1984 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Photographs of Weigel at various speaking engagements and gatherings, undated (Folder 13: 7)